Finding Aid for Marjorie Cahn Brazer papers, 1955-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marjorie Cahn Brazer papers 1955-1992
Brazer, Marjorie Cahn.
8551 Aa 2
Secretary of the Ann Arbor (Mich.) Transportation Authority (AATA). Minutes, 1969-1973, financial statements, reports, and photographs of the AATA largely concerning the problems of mass transportation and the development of the "Dial-a-Ride" system; also papers concerning the development of streets and automobile parking facilities in the city.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Marjorie Cahn Brazer (donor no. 5968 ) and first came to the library in 1977.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marjorie Cahn Brazer, scholar and community leader, was for thirty years active in the civic and political affairs of Detroit and Ann Arbor beginning in the mid-1950s and continuing nearly up until her death in 1992. Born in 1927, she received her B.A. from Antioch College and her M.A. from Lehigh University. She lived in Detroit in the early 1950s and then moved to Ann Arbor in 1957 when her husband, Harvey Brazer, became a professor of economics at the University of Michigan.
Throughout her life, Marjorie Brazer was a firm believer in the value of citizen participation in local community affairs. She demonstrated this through membership in a myriad of organizational affiliations and through her advocacy of intergovernmental partnerships, women's political rights, and racial justice. Her public activism began in Detroit with participation in the local League of Women Voters. In Detroit, she also involved herself in the issue of urban renewal and neighborhood preservation through membership on the Detroit Committee for Neighborhood Conservation and Improved Housing.
Following her move to Ann Arbor, Brazer involved herself in her new community. In addition to becoming active in the local League of Women Voters, she helped to found (in her own living room) the Ann Arbor Area Association (soon renamed the Citizen's Association for Area Planning, CAAP). Through CAAP, Brazer participated in studies pertaining to Ann Arbor development, helped to influence city laws on the Briarwood Development (1971); and was active in issues relating to historic preservation and city planning.
In the 1960s, Brazer was a member of the Washtenaw County Citizen's Committee for Economic Opportunity (CEO), running the program office during its campaign for legal aid reform in 1965-66. She also joined the Coalition for Racial Justice and was on the Bi-Racial Committee of Huron High School. Brazer tried elective political office herself, running unsuccessfully for the office of county supervisor. During this same period, she served as a consulting economist for the Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (1961-64), the Washtenaw County Metropolitan Planning Commission (1964-65), and the Michigan Department of Commerce (1965-66).
Perhaps her most lasting impact came with her work with the Ann Arbor Transportation Authority. As charter member and one-time acting Director of AATA, Brazer was instrumental in creating a public transportation system for urban (primarily Ann Arbor) Washtenaw County in the early 1970s. During her period of service, Ann Arbor established the Dial-a-Ride program.
Among her other interests was historical research, she was a lecturer at Eastern Michigan University and historian and biographer of eighteenth-century fur trader John Johnston. In 1990 she and her husband moved to Brutus, a resort town in Emmet County, Michigan, where she died in January 1992.
The Marjorie C. Brazer Papers covers the period of 1955 to 1983 and has been arranged mainly by the name of organization in which Brazer participated. The largest portion of the collection - Ann Arbor Transportation Authority - consists of minutes, policy and long-range planning documents, and subject files detailing the process by which the bus service for Ann Arbor was established, and the beginning of the Dial-a-Ride program. Other smaller organization files in the collection pertain to the Citizen's Association for Area Planning, the Detroit Committee for Neighborhood Conservation and Improved Housing, the Huron High Bi-Racial Committee, the League of Women Voters (Detroit), the League of Women Voters (Ann Arbor), and the Washtenaw County Citizens Committee for Economic Opportunity. One file - Washtenaw County Political Campaigns - concerns Lloyd Ives' 1959 Ann Arbor mayoral campaign and Brazer's own 1968 campaign for county supervisor. Of interest is the documentation of an oral history project undertaken by Brazer in 1983 and pertaining to the establishment and operation of the Rackham endowment to the University of Michigan. This includes oral history sound cassettes and administrative files for the project. Brazer's work on this project resulted in her Biography of an Endowment, published in 1985 by the Bentley Historical Library.
Subjects:
Dial-A-Ride (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor Transportation Authority.; Automobile parking--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Roads--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Transportation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women in public life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Buses.; Dial-A-Ride (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Main Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Mass transit--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Maynard Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; University of Michigan--History.; Horace H. Rackham and Mary A. Rackham Fund.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Brazer, Marjorie Cahn.; Briggs, Robert Peter, 1903-; Cudlip, William B., 1904-1988; Kelly, E. Lowell (Everett Lowell), 1905-1986; Dawson, William Ryan, 1927-; Duff, Ivan Francis, 1915-; Fine, Sidney, 1920-; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Host, Margaret.; Manupelli, George.; Rolland, Ivan.; Shapiro, Harold T., 1935-; Stokes, Donald E.; Sussman, Alfred S.; Wethey, Harold E. (Harold Edwin), 1902-1984.; Schlanderer, Frances Knapp.; Smith, Mark W.; Weigant, Lee.; Elving, Philip Juliber, 1913-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Organizational activities
  - Ann Arbor Transportation Authority 1969-1975
    - Briarwood Shopping Center 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Dial-a-ride
      - General 1969-1975, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Financial reports 1969-1973 (Box 1)
    - Long range policy and planning reports and studies 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Minutes and agenda 1969-1974 (Box 1)
      (incomplete)
    - Teltran Citizens Committee 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Vinter-AATA controversy (Box 1)
  - Citizen's Association for Area Planning
    - Briarwood Impact 1971 (Box 1)
    - Growth Study 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Historic Preservation Committee 1967-1973 (Box 1)
    - Organizational Papers 1964-1974 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Committee for Neighborhood conservation a Improved Housing 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Huron High School (Ann Arbor) Bi-Racial Committee
    - Minutes and Reports 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Minutes and Reports 1970-1971, Grievance Policy appendix (Box 2)
  - League of Women Voters--Ann Arbor
    - 1957-1959 (Box 2)
      (include Unit Organizing and Urban Renewal Committee)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 2)
      (include League Bulletins and Program & Action papers)
  - League of Women Voters--Detroit 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Citizen's Committee for Economic Opportunity 1966 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Political Campaigns (Box 2)
- Other projects and miscellaneous
  - Rackham Endowment oral history project 1983
    - Sound recordings (Box 2)
    - Administrative files (Box 2)
  - Family miscellaneous (Box 2)
    (include publications of poetry published in high schools, etc.)